The year 1985. NASA researcher Rick Briggs wrote —
सन् १९८५। नासा के वैज्ञानिक रिक ब्रिग्स ने लिखा —
Sanskrit is the world's most suitable language for computers.
संस्कृत, कंप्यूटर के लिए दुनिया की सबसे उपयुक्त भाषा है।
And its foundation? About 2,500 years ago, Panini wrote 4,000 sutras
और इसकी नींव? आज से लगभग ढाई हज़ार साल पहले पाणिनि ने चार हज़ार सूत्रों में
describing the entire grammar of the language — exactly like a program.
पूरी भाषा का व्याकरण लिख दिया — बिल्कुल किसी प्रोग्राम की तरह।
See the power of Sanskrit — every word is spoken exactly as it is written.
संस्कृत की शक्ति देखिए — हर शब्द वैसा ही बोला जाता है, जैसा लिखा जाता है।
Every sentence, perfectly unambiguous. As if this language were made for computers.
हर वाक्य का अर्थ — बिल्कुल स्पष्ट। मानो यह भाषा कंप्यूटर के लिए ही बनी हो।
So we thought — a language this perfect, could it not become a programming language itself? Why not!
तो हमने सोचा — जो भाषा इतनी परिपूर्ण है, क्या वह स्वयं एक प्रोग्रामिंग भाषा नहीं बन सकती? क्यों नहीं!
That is why we built — Sanskrita! A real programming language, entirely in Sanskrit.
इसीलिए हमने बनाई — संस्कृता! असली प्रोग्रामिंग भाषा, पूरी तरह संस्कृत में।
Vada. Yadi. Yaavat. Vidhi. And Panini's karakas too.
वद। यदि। यावत्। विधि। और पाणिनि के कारक भी।
This is no translation — it has its own engine. Decimals always exact. Sandhi and meter — built into the language itself.
यह कोई अनुवाद नहीं — इसका अपना इंजन है। दशमलव हमेशा शुद्ध। संधि और छन्द — भाषा के भीतर ही बने हुए।
Our dream — Sanskrita standing proudly among the world's finest languages. Open source — for everyone, free forever.
हमारा सपना — संस्कृता दुनिया की श्रेष्ठ भाषाओं के बीच गर्व से खड़ी हो। ओपन सोर्स — सबके लिए, हमेशा मुफ़्त।
And this is only the beginning. Jayatu Sanskritam!
और यह तो केवल शुरुआत है। जयतु संस्कृतम्!